Guide to the Cornell University College of Architecture, Art and Planning student projects,1898-2006.
Cornell University College of Architecture, Art and Planning student projects,1898-2006
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Cornell University College of Architecture, Art and Planning student projects, 1898-2006.
15-5-1416
Cornell University.College of Architecture, Art and Planning.
29 cubic ft.
Reports, Research Materials, Scrapbooks
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Volumes containing honors designs and theses; an interscholastic competition; and merit solutions for landscape design, also, student projects and drawings, and photographs of projects.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Volumes containing honors designs and theses; an interscholastic competition; and merit solutions for landscape design, 1912-1922. Also, student projects and drawings, and photographs of projects, 1903-1967; three banners and one plaque for the Inter College Athletic Championships, 1910-1916; approximately 300 student pen and ink sketches, primarily copied from published works; and student projects for the Dept. of City and Regional Planning. Includes drawings of Cornell University and Ithaca buildings, such as Sage College, Boardman and Cascadilla Halls, Llenroc, the Grant Mansion, Giles House and student apartments, as well as proposed residential halls and academic buildings. Also, drawings of historic European and classical structures, and architectural elements. Among the students and architects whose work is represented are Carráere & Hastings, Richard C. Murdock (Cornell University Class of 1927), John Wellborn Root (Cornell University Class of 1909), and Robert J. Eidlitz (Cornell University Class of 1885).
Includes design problems, 1922-1954.
Includes Baird Prize competition "Place Plate" artwork from Design 112, February 1932. The winning design (not included) was used by the Wedgwood Company for a set of twelve plates depicting Cornell scenes.
Drawing on canvas by Richard Andrews Tissington (written RA Tissington), who graduated from the College of Architecture in 1900. According to a 1901 publication of Cornell Alumni News, the drawing, entitled "Design for a Ceiling," was the First Prize Drawing in the Cornell Traveling Fellowship Competition. It was also featured in a exhibit for the Convention of the Architectural League of America May 23-25, 1901. The drawing itself is approximately 48"x60"and is extremely fragile.
Framed rendering of a design for an "Alumni Hall - East Elevation. Cornell University" created as a student project by Samuel R. DeLong, Class of 1895, Architecture.
A 2000 "Praxis2" booklet compiled as the final report of a collaborative Architecture/Planning Course working with the Ithaca Neighborhood Housing Services on a site design for a housing development on West Hill in Ithaca, N.Y.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cornell University.; Eidlitz, Robert James, 1864-1935.; Murdock, Richard C.; Root, John Wellborn, 1887-1963.; Carráere & Hastings.; Cornell University--Buildings.; Cornell University.Dept. of City and Regional Planning.
Subjects:
Architecture--Study and teaching.; City planning.; Landscape architecture.
Places:
Ithaca (N.Y.)--Buildings.
Form and Genre Terms:
Architectural drawings.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
A partial guide of the project titles in the collection and names of their creators is available here, PDF file. A new series 1926-1927 starts on page 126 of the guide.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Miscellaneous Projects 1885 - 1997
Box 1-6, 35-39
Series II. Theses 1926-1931 (Vol. I-V)
Box 13
Series III. Interscholastic Competition (Vol. I of I)
Box 13
Series IV. Merit Solutions, Landscape Design 1912-1922 (Vol. 1-10)
Boxes 14,15
Series Va. Honors designs 1898/1899 - 1946/1947
Boxes 7-11, 16-23, 27-31
Series Vb. Honors designs 1947/1948 - 1951/1952 and 1952/1953 - 1956/1957
Boxes 24-26
Series VI. Design Problems, 1922/1923 - 1958/1959
Box 32
Series VII. Thesis Programs Series VIII. Other 1939-1951
Boxes 33,34
Series VIII. Other
Box 40
Series IX. Oversized Items
Mapcase
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Miscellanous Projects 1885 - 1997
  - 35 Folders: Sub-Theses, 1947-1967 (Box 1)
  - "Photographics Reproductions" (Scrapbook), Richard. C. Murdock, 1927 (Box 2)
  - 5" x 7" Envelopes Containing Drawings by Other Students, 1987 (Box 2)
  - "Problems in Mechanics" (Scrapbook) (AM W.drawings), Warren .P. Laird, Class in Mechanics, Cornell University, 1885-1886 (Box 3)
  - "Housing-Whose Responsibility?" (CRP Conference), Dept. of City and Regional Planning Publications, 1960 (Box 4)
  - "Cortland, NY General Plan", 1954-1955 (Box 4)
  - "Johnson City, NY General Plan", 1958-1959 (Box 4)
  - "Chemung County Urban Area", Fall 1964 (Box 4)
  - Dept. of City and Regional Planning Plans (Box 5)
    Includes Schohane Valley Townsite, Auburn General Plan
  - 4 Folders: Theses on Planning by Various Students, Including Raymond G. Ballard, Donald Beach, Allan Ray Cooper, and Arnold Nye (Box 6)
  - Miesuse: toward the mesoforms edited by Julián Varas., 2006 (Box 6)
    Miesuse is a design research project developed in collaboration with a team of architecture students at Cornell University between January and May 2006. The project is part of an investigation on techniques of formal production in architecture, and it seeks to establish lines of continuity and transformation on the basis of spatial concepts developed by Mies van der Rohe during the period 1920-1945.
  - Other student projects, course descriptions, ca. 1980 (Box 35-38)
  - Student work for the National Architectural Accrediting Board, 1997 (Box 39)
  - Lysander New City, a project for fourth and fifth year students, 1970 (Box 39)
  - "Praxis2" booklet, 2000 (Box 39)
  - Building design sketches, Single folder
- Series II. Theses 1926-1931 (Vol. I-V)
  - Volume I, 1926-1927 (Box 13)
  - Volume II, 1927-1928 (Box 13)
  - Volume III, 1928-1929 (Box 13)
  - Volume IV, 1929-1930 (Box 13)
  - Volume V, 1930-1931 (Box 13)
- Series III. Interscholastic Competition (Vol. I of I)
  - Volume I (Box 13)
- Series IV. Merit Solutions, Landscape Design 1912-1922 (Vol. 1-10)
  - Volume 1, 1911-1912, 1912-1913 (Box 14)
  - Volume 2, 1913-1914 (Box 14)
  - Volume 3, 1914-1915 (Box 14)
  - Volume 4, 1915-1916 (Box 14)
  - Volume 5, 1916-1917 (Box 14)
  - Volume 6, 1917-1918 (Box 15)
  - Volume 7, 1918-1919 (Box 15)
  - Volume 8, 1919-1920 (Box 15)
  - Volume 9, 1920-1921 (Box 15)
  - Volume 10, 1921-1922 (Box 15)
- Series Va. Honors designs 1898/1899 - 1946/1947
  - Volume I, 1898-1899 (Box 16)
  - Volume II-III, 1899-1901 (Box 16)
  - Volume IV, 1901-1905 (Box 16)
  - Volume V, 1904-1905 (Box 16)
  - Volume VI, 1905-1906 (Box 11)
  - Volume VII, 1906-1907 (Box 11)
  - Volume VIII, 1907-1908 (Box 17)
  - Volume IX, 1908-1909 (Box 11)
  - Volume X, 1909-1910 (Box 10)
  - Volume XI, 1910-1911 (Box 17)
  - Volume XII, 1911-1912 (Box 17)
  - Volume XIII, 1912-1913 (Box 17)
  - Volume XIV, 1913-1914 (Box 18)
  - Volume XV, 1914-1915 (Box 10)
  - Volume XVI, 1915-1916 (Box 18)
  - Volume XVII, 1916-1919 (Box 18)
  - Volume XVIII, 1917-1918 (Box 19)
  - Volume XIX, 1918-1919 (Box 19)
  - Volume XX, 1919-1920 (Box 19)
  - Volume XXI, 1920-1921
  - Volume XXII, 1921-1922 (Box 19)
  - Volume XXIII, 1922-1923 (Box 20)
  - Volume XXIV, 1923-1924 (Box 20)
  - Volume XXV, 1924-1925 (Box 20)
  - Volume XXVI (A), 1925-1926 (Box 21)
  - Volume XXVI (B), 1925-1926 (Box 21)
  - Volume XXVII, 1926-1927 (Box 21)
  - Volume XXVIII, 1927-1928 (Box 10)
  - Volume XXIX, 1928-1929 (Box 11)
  - Volume XXX, 1929-1930 (Box 21)
  - Volume XXXI, 1930-1931 (Box 22)
  - Volume XXXII, 1931-1932 (Box 22)
  - Volume XXXIII, 1932-1933 (Box 10)
  - Volume XXXIV, 1933-1934 (Box 22)
  - Volume XXXV, 1934-1935 (Box 22)
  - Volume XXXVI, 1936-1937 (Box 7)
  - Volume XXXVII, 1936-1937 (Box 8)
  - Volume XXXVIII, 1937-1938 (Box 8)
  - Volume XXXIX, 1938-1939 (Box 23)
  - Volume XL, 1939-1940 (Box 9)
  - Volume XLI, 1940-1941 (Box 27)
  - Volume XLII, 1941-1942 (Box 28)
  - Volume XLIII (Old Series), 1942-1943 (Box 29)
  - Volume XLIV (Old Series) (Loose on Shelf), 1943-1944
  - Volume XLV (Old Series), 1944-1945 (Box 30)
  - Volume XLVI (Old Series), 1945-1946 (Box 31)
  - Volume XLVII, 1946-1947 (Box 23)
- Series Vb. Honors designs 1947/1948 - 1951/1952 and 1952/1953 - 1956/1957
  - Volume XLIII (1) (New Series), 1947-1948 (Box 24)
  - Volume XLIII (2) (New Series), 1947-1948 (Box 24)
  - Volume XIV (1) (New Series), 1948-1949 (Box 24)
  - Volume XIV (2) (New Series), 1948-1949 (Box 25)
  - Volume XLV (1) (New Series), 1949-1950 (Box 25)
  - Volume XLV (2) (New Series), 1949-1950 (Box 25)
  - Volume XLVI (1) (New Series), 1950-1951 (Box 25)
  - Volume XLVI (2) (New Series), 1950-1951 (Box 26)
  - Volume XVII (New Series), 1951-1952 (Box 26)
  - Un-Numbered Volume, 1952-1953 (Box 26)
  - Un-Numbered Volume, 1953-1954 (Box 26)
  - Volume I, 1954-1955 (Box 26)
  - Volume I, 1956-1957 (Box 26)
- Series VI. Design Problems, 1922/1923 - 1958/1959
  - Design Problems - In Folders Arranged Chronologically, 1922/1923 - 1958/1959 (Box 32)
- Series VII. Thesis Programs 1939-1951
  - Thesis Programs (In Folders) (Box 33)
  - Thesis Programs (In Folders) (Box 34)
- Series VIII. Other
  - Baird Prize competition "Place Plate" artwork from Design 112 (Box 40)
- Series IX. Oversized Items
  - Giles Manse, Ithaca, NY (Map-case Folder 1)
  - Robert Eidlitz (Map-case Folder 2-3)
  - Early student projects (Map-case Folder 4-5)
  - Charles Babcock (Map-case Folder 6)
  - Printed items (Map-case Folder 7)
  - "Mirrors of White Hall", an anonymously printed sheet, n.d. (Map-case Folder 8)
  - "Design for a Ceiling", by Richard Andrews Tissington, ca. 1900 (Map-case Folder 9)
  - Large framed rendering of design for "Alumni Hall - East Elevation, Cornell University", by Samuel R. DeLong, ca. 1895 (Map-case Item)